On that day during summer vacation,
you knew that the school would go adrift.
So why did you still go?
That's right, I knew everything.
And that's why I did—
I couldn't just leave everyone to it.
But what was the point?
Well...
Did they ask for your salvation?
Is this world a movie theater?
No, this is no ordinary movie theater.
Is this...
It's your point of view.
Skimming through this, it looks like
the whole film was shot from your perspective.
I...
d-don't have a hidden camera or anything!
I know!
Then who on earth did this?
I can't say I know for sure yet,
but this might be the first world that shows us other worlds.
This may be some sort of special place.
Have you not found Nagara yet?!
It's been two months!
What the hell have you been doing?!
Sir, yes, sir!
He appears to be constantly moving from world to world,
and we can't seem to locate him using the power relics, sir!
He's not capable of coming up with
anything that intelligent on his own.
He must have collaborators working with him!
They are just as guilty!
Find them, no matter the cost!
Sir, yes, sir!
Mizuho sure is taking her time. I'm starving.
She should be here any moment now.
I have some chocolate if you want some.
Sure.
A-A stray dog?!
Mmm, you smell good.
The sweet smell of chocolate.
I-It talked!
The dog talked!
Shake!
Sit!
Sit up!
Allow me to introduce you. This is Yamabiko.
It sounds like he drifted into this world, just like us.
He said he used to be human,
but suddenly transformed at some point.
There, there, there...
Pleasure to meet you.
A veteran castaway... dog?
Ugh, that stinks.
If you're a castaway like us,
does that mean you're also in stasis?
That's right.
Then why are you a dog?
Is it some sort of power?
Dog or not, I'm still myself.
You see? I haven't—
So where have you been all this time?
I was living in the forest, but the storm
that came through drove me out of there.
Does he mean Asakaze?
Most likely.
Do you know...
what's causing this drifting?
That I don't know.
Are we ever going to get home?
Many who came before me attempted to get back to their own world,
but none have been successful.
Though that doesn't mean there's no hope.
Huh? So we can go home?!
Yes...
There's still time.
It hasn't been a year since you got here, right?
Whew, we're so close to being finished.
That's right.
We just have to collect the material for its core.
Do we really not have to go looking for it?
Apparently it's going to come to us.
Hey.
How's things?
It sure has been a while, hasn't it?
What have you been up to all this time?
We've been hopping between different worlds with Nagara,
looking for the piece we need to get us back home.
Hey, why don't we all go home together?
I think we've already given you our answer to that.
The outcome is already decided.
We can't go home.
Our only choice is to live here.
Don't give me that nonsense about the outcome already being decided.
Isn't it up to youngsters like us to keep trying anyway?
We're inside the light right now.
Just one step away.
I never imagined there was someone adrift longer than us.
He said there was still time.
That we're still connected.
Yeah, he did.
Could he mean that whatever is holding that connection in place
might be somewhere in this world?
Yeah, could be.
Provided that your power is what created these worlds,
and that you held this power even in our world,
the school might have been
something akin to another world.
And if that's true, then maybe there's a film of our world in here, too.
The fact that we weren't the first ones to go adrift,
and that it happened to others from our school,
might support that theory.
You guys seem to have gotten the wrong impression.
I was also a 3rd-year student at Shiraito Middle School No. 2,
the same as all of you.
Huh? From the same school?
Then we're classmates?!
Who are you? What's your name?
Yamada Kunihiko.
Was there anyone there with that name?
It's no surprise that you wouldn't know me.
See, I enrolled the year that you graduated.
Wait, then that means...
Isn't that strange?
That would mean that you're here from the future.
Space-time is flexible.
How long have you been here, then?
5,000 years.
But when he says 5,000 years,
it just doesn't seem real, does it?
Plus, he turned into a dog.
Whoa! What just happened?!
Huh?!
S-Sorry!
Are you okay?
What did you just do?
This is footage of us since we moved to the island.
Fetch.
Come on!
Let's try a little experiment.
Okay.
This is an app I made for video editing.
Does that mean...
It sure does.
Any changes to the film also have an effect on the real world.
Let's experiment a little more.
These are the images from that film.
Now we add something else—
like the great Monkey Mountain.
Fascinating, isn't it?
By editing two worlds together,
we can create a composite.
Amazing. You could do anything.
Actually, I already tried this once...
But nothing happened.
The only difference now is that you're here taking part in the preview.
Which means that simply editing the film doesn't alter the world.
The crucial element is whether or not you're here watching it.
Okay, then what would happen if we played it backwards?
There's trouble on the horizon.
Are you sure we should be leaving this up to them?
You mean those delicate little mice?
They're as pure as can be,
and haven't gotten any preferential treatment.
They need me to watch over them.
We just need to keep an eye on those brats
who are overconfident in the powers
they've been given and dare to defy God.
Their plot would bring about the end of the world.
The end of the world?
Yeah. We have to prevent that, whatever it takes.
You're the only one who can protect everyone.
You understand that, right?
There's nothing to fear.
Your power and my sense of relativity were made for each other.
Hey, are you ever coming back?
I'd love to get the gang together again.
You've got Nagara, right?
Yeah, Nagara's giving it his all.
He's trying to prove to himself that he can stand up to the world.
Our very own Nagara!
Looks like playing it backwards goes against the rules of this world.
I was thinking we could go back to before we went adrift,
but I guess it's not that easy.
We can see the past, but we can't change it.
Which means that effects can't happen without their causes.
What's this?
Oh, that one's no good.
It's been eaten by mold, and it's the wrong size.
Is this...
You really are special.
We might be able to go home now.
So you have a new project, then?
I do. I call it the "Director's Cut" project.
What's that?
A director's cut is when a movie that has already been in theaters
gets re-edited, and becomes a remade production.
In the same way, I'm thinking of having us do a director's cut.
Of what?
Of ourselves and this world.
We are castaways who ended up in this world by mistake.
And over here, we have another reel of film that Nagara found.
This film shows our own world,
where we're supposed to be.
Wow, that takes me back!
But you were a transfer student.
Oh, right.
We're going to paste ourselves in here where we're missing,
and re-edit our own world.
We're going to remake our own world ourselves.
Who's gonna pull off something as ambitious as that?
Nagara, right?
That's right.
Even if it's a hurdle we can't get over, Nagara is able to.
But we can change the future as much as we like.
We can't change the past.
What if the future is already decided?
We already know how it turns out.
Is knowing really all that great?
Yeah. I am that great.
No matter how impressive you are,
you can't change the future.
You should use your power in a way that's more helpful to all of us.
This shelter, you see, is actually an ark.
With it, I will save us all from the coming disaster.
It's not like we asked for this.
Did you say something?
Nagara's right. Hoshi, we ought to—
Even if the outcome is set in stone,
I'm not running from it.
Yeah.
Cap, have I ever been wrong about anything?
I don't believe in keeping to the beaten path,
No.
But even so...
then breathing a sigh of relief when you arrive safely.
That's not how you should live your life.
Oh dear.
Nagara, I think it's about time to relocate to another world.
Let's quit this, already.
No matter how many power relics we collect,
we'll never be able to beat Asakaze and the others.
I'm starting to wonder if we were wrong after all.
Is it true that you were able to change the world?
Yeah. It worked perfectly in our experiments,
for the most part.
For the most part?
Yeah... There are times when the editing works,
and times when it doesn't.
It seems like there's some kind of random chance at play.
Are you sure we'll be all right?
Nothing strange is going to happen?
No, nothing like that.
This is based on the fact that only things that can happen will happen.
You being who you are isn't going to change.
Are you sure?
You'll be fine! You're not going to suddenly turn into a dog or anything.
For one thing, this world is set up so that things work in the students' favor.
Why are only students who went to our school going adrift?
That's because the principal is God.
Huh?
The principal? You mean our principal?
This drifting was brought about according to His will.
Huh? But why would God be our principal?
It's nothing more than simple coincidence.
He just happened to be the principal.
He just happened to be?
But even if that's so,
what is the point of us going adrift?
There is no point.
Nil.
It's from Ace. He says they want to meet up.
Huh?! Why now, after everything they put Nagara through?!
Let them come.
Huh? Seriously?
If they've taken the steps to contacting us,
they must have seen the error of their ways.
Besides, if they're in trouble,
we should extend a helping hand.
Make them beg! Make them beg!
This is what the ark is for.
Okay, this is where we'll do it.
This is where we'll build our ark.
Ark?
Yeah. I have to save everyone.
You understand, right?
You see, I want to save all of you.
Hey, are you sure we shouldn't be helping Rajdhani and the others?
Why?
Well...
Because the way things are going,
it seems like we're never going home.
And what if we don't?
Even if we never go home,
it has no bearing on our previous world.
You're going to save everyone.
I just want to save everyone.
Did they ask for your salvation?
Are you sure this is the way to go?
Just doing exactly as you're told...
It isn't like you.
If we get home tomorrow,
we'll be just in time for our graduation.
Do you think we could still graduate after missing this much school?
Who knows?
You can't fly anymore.
Today's our graduation ceremony.
Bye.
Our shelter has now become an ark.
When will you finally understand?!
Give it up, already!
Ms. Aki! Listen to me, please!
It's not possible for this project to cause the end of the world!
No, it is ending!
A teacher?
No, that can't be.
Why not?
All that ever goes adrift are the school and its students.
Huh? But...
There's no choice but for you to stay!
Stop them.
Is Nagara doing this?
The world really has changed.
Great, looks like it worked.
Let's move on to the project. Agreed?
Yeah, okay.
Let's give it a try.
They said they're ready whenever.
We're ready here, too.
Okay, let's all go home together!
Yeah.
Honestly, what are we going to do about your mother?
Can't you just make a decision on your own already?
We need to do more than just discuss this over and over.
Huh? What's that?
Miss!
When did that get there?
There's a dead bird at the front gate.
It's gross. Please do something about it.
Don't tell me you...
It's not right to take things out on those weaker than you.
No, that isn't what I...
What is it?
The light...
The light is here.
The light?
The one you've been talking about?
Yeah.
We were right after all!
You are all no longer needed.
Asakaze!
Is this...
I'm... here.
What a pity.
You always have to screen the future to see what will happen.
What do you mean?
You were not creating worlds.
You were just an observer,
opening boxes of possibilities.
This world exists because you are here.
You are simply copies.
Huh?
What's going on?
We were not chosen.
There's another me here.
We no longer have a place to go home to.
I get it. This wasn't us going adrift—
it was God rolling the dice.
Did you really think that you were the only special ones?
They ended up failing, huh?
They were so close, too.
Congratulations on your graduation!
Are you sure that this was for the best?
Yeah. The world has been preserved.
Sorry.
It didn't work.
It's not your fault, Nagara.
In the end, it was a matter of probability.
That's true.
There was a chance that we would become the originals.
I've underestimated you, Nagara.
Hey, I thought you said there was still time.
Eight months fits within the margin of error of life.
There's no chance left for me, though.
We have to get going.
I was dead.
Huh?
So what could the light have been, then?